-==www.RagBear.com==-
是, 首相  第2季第2集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译: smapwestlife
校对&时间轴: tpring
官方保密
好 各位 今天的议程是审核
Gentlemen, we're here to consider security clearance
我前任的回忆录的最新一章
for the publication of my predecessor's memoirs.
副检察长
Solicitor General.
对 各位知道 我们已经通过了1至7章
We've already approved chapters 1 to 7.
我看没有理由不通过第8章
I see no reason to withhold approval for 8.
等等 我觉得有些材料很成问题
There is some highly questionable material.
哪些?      好 就从211页说起
Such as? Well, page 211, for a start.
不过是"行政事务大臣在内阁支持"
It only says, "The Administrative Affairs Minister supported
"扩建塞拉菲尔德核燃料厂"
the expansion of Sellafield in Cabinet,
"却又公开反对"      说的是我 我就是行政大臣
"but spoke out against it in public." I was the minister.
问题是 这不算泄密      可它不实啊
The point is it's not a security leak. But it isn't true.
文章本身确实很震撼 可恕我直言 首相
The documentation is fairly impressive, but with respect,
如果他诽谤您 只能出版之后告上法庭
if he's libelled you, it's a matter for the courts,
出版前的安检委员会管不着
not for the Security Clearance Committee.
怎么能让这种指控传出去 还不止211页
We can't have such accusations. It's not just page 211.
224页又有个恶毒指控 说我停止化工厂计划
On 224, about my stopping that chemical-plant project
是害怕媒体的空穴来风
because of a baseless press scare.
更站不住脚的一段出现在231页
Then there's an indefensible passage about me on page 231.
231页 "哈克关心选票更胜于原则"
Oh, 231. "Hacker was more interested in votes than principles,
"一见风声不对 拔腿就跑"
"running for cover at the first whiff of unpopularity.
"他提升了内阁平均年龄 却降低了平均智商"
"He raised the average age of Cabinet but lowered the average IQ."
谢谢 汉弗莱 我们都看过这章了
Thank you, Humphrey. We've all read the chapter.
对 可首相 我说过 我对他的话不置可否
As I said, I'm not supporting or defending him,
可这确实不算泄密
but it's not an actual security breach.
再说 第5章也泄漏了 我们也没管
Chapter 5 got leaked and we took no action.
第五章高度赞扬了
Oh, well, chapter 5 was very complimentary about
我跟库朗谈成的合同
my getting the Kumran contract.
还有我的电脑保安规章
about my computer security guideline
这里面的机密信息一样多
It had as much confidential material
您甚至没发起泄密调查
and you never had a leak inquiry.
这章谁都可能漏给媒体嘛
Well... anybody could have leaked that chapter to the press.
谁都可能
Anybody.
我说 第8章就连标题...      "吉姆哈克的双面人生"
even the title of chapter 8 "2 Faces Of Jim Hacker."
这总不算秘密吧
Er, that's not a secret, surely.
抱歉 我觉得有安全隐患
I think there are security implications.
塞拉菲尔德造的是核燃料
Sellafield is nuclear.
可主管塞拉菲尔德的能源大臣
The Energy Secretary has seen the chapter
也看过了 他也没意见
and he says he has no problems.
他当然没问题 里面管他叫
No! It describes him as the
内阁最能干的大臣 又抹黑我一次
ablest minister in Cabinet. Another slur on me.
这不能入罪      我们挑明了说
It isn't actionable. Let's be clear.
我们有权拒绝出版 对吧?      是有权
We have the right to refuse publication. We have.
可如果他们无视我们 硬要出版
If they publish anyway,
我的法律意见是 别指望靠法庭制止
we'll have no hope of stopping it through the courts.
那只能指望出版社了      用什么理由?
Lean on the publishers. On what grounds?
国家利益      我已经解释了...
National interest. I've already...
这是无耻下流 国家利益岂能容忍
It's obscene filth. It cannot be in the national interest
取笑国家领导人...
to ridicule the national leader.
我是说...破坏国家领导层公信力
I mean... undermine confidence in the national leadership.
第8章绝不能出版 好吗?
Chapter 8 must not be published, right?
好啊 伯纳      不太好 汉弗莱爵士
Well, Bernard? No, not very, Sir Humphrey.
首相看过了吗?
Has the PM seen that yet?
我不知道 不过"今日头条"播了摘要
They quoted it on "Today".
他吃早餐时应该听见了
He'd have listened to it while he had breakfast.
我也听说了 他被人当早餐吃了
I heard it. They had HIM for breakfast.
是啊 最受欢迎的是
They had fun with,
"吉姆哈克提高了内阁平均年龄"
"Jim Hacker raised the average age of the Cabinet...
"却拉低了平均智商" 是啊
(BOTH) "...but lowered the average IQ."
说实话 是挺有意思      确实不假 可是 另一方面...
it is rather amusing. Yes But on the other hand...
我知道 你怎么解释这次泄漏?
I know. Have you any explanation for this leak?
不是我干的 汉弗莱爵士      当然不是你
It wasn't me. Of course it wasn't you!
泄漏这一章对你对我都没好处
It's hardly in your interest or mine to leak THAT chapter.
不光是第8章本身 还有他想封杀它的事
it's the report that he tried to suppress it.
所以只能是与会的人干的
The leak came from someone at the meeting.
早上好 汉弗莱爵士
Good morning.
他为什么这么想?      他有没有...已经...
What makes him think that? Is he... er...? Has he...
新闻办挤着全国一半媒体 等他回话
Half of Britain's press corps are here waiting for his response.
才一半?      另一半在打电话
Only half? The other half are on the phone.
境外媒体也注意到了
The foreign press have picked it up.
申请采访的有"世界报" "华盛顿邮报"
I've had interview requests from "Le Monde", the "Washington Post",
还有"时尚女装"
and "Women's Wear Daily".
你看他会作何反应?
How do you think he'll take it?
我们就快知道了
We're just about to find out.
嗯?
Well?
嗯? 说话啊
Well? Well, say something.
早上好 首相      早上好 首相
Good morning, Prime Minister. Good morning, Prime Minister.
看见了吗? 你是宣传秘书 比尔
Seen this? You're my press secretary, Bill.
你知道这是灭顶之灾
It's a catastrophe!
出于尊重 首相...      一点也不尊重 汉弗莱
With respect... With no respect at all!
不尊重国家机密 不尊重国家利益 不尊重国家领导人
No respect for confidentiality, national interest or the leader!
不可原谅 谁泄漏的?      问谁去?
Who leaked it? Who can say?
就问你 你最好有个答复 我要求马上追查
You can say and you'd better say! I want this traced at once!
一定是昨天与会的某个人
It must've been somebody at the meeting.
我这就发起泄密调查
I'll set up a leak inquiry.
我不要泄密调查 我要找出谁干的
I don't want a leak inquiry. I want to find out who did it.
首相 发生泄密的时候 通常没人想知道谁干的
One normally doesn't want to find out who's responsible
万一是内阁成员就麻烦了
in case it turns out to be one of the Cabinet.
只有副检察长和我
The Solicitor General and I were the
两名内阁成员出席 不会是他 检察官从不泄密
only ministers present. Law officers never leak.
再说对他也没好处
He had nothing to gain,
也不是我 剩下都是公务员
it wasn't me and all the rest were officials.
我要一路告上法庭去
I will pursue this through to the courts!
首相 您得给我个回话 媒体都在等着
The press are all waiting.
4家电视台要求采访 还有11家广播电台
There are four requests for TV interviews and eleven for radio.
绝了 上周我千方百计告诉他们
Marvellous. Last week, I was dying to tell them
我如何缓和英苏局势 没人要听
about my achieving detente with the Soviets.
这下倒好 都跟一堆鹫鹰似的撵上来了
Now this happens and they charge in like a herd of vultures.
不是一堆 首相
Not herd, Prime Minister.
跟一堆鹫鹰一样...
(CLEARLY) Charge in like a herd...
鹫鹰不论堆 它们论群
Vultures don't herd, they flock.
而且它们不是撵 它们...
And they don't charge, they... er...
它们怎样 伯纳?      它们...
What do they do, Bernard? They... er...
坐下 伯纳
Sit down, Bernard.
媒体怎么就不能为国家着想?
Why can't the press support Britain?
干嘛非要揭丑闻 怎么不写写我们的成就?
Why do they muck-rake? Why can't they write about our successes?
比如...      比如我缓和了对苏关系
Like... er...? Well, like my detente with the Soviets.
苏联政府确实松口了些 可没什么实质举动
There are noises from the Kremlin, but nothing concrete.
就会有的啊      很抱歉 首相
It's going to. I'm sorry.
可我必须给他们个说法
I have to tell them something
关于您试图封杀前首相回忆录的事
about you trying to suppress your predecessor's memoirs.
很好 私下跟他们说 "首相亲信表示"
Talk to them off the record. "Sources close to the PM."
不要署名      好
Say nothing attributable. Right.
就说 他对我的描述谎话连篇
Say that what he said about me is a pack of lies.
您是说..."拔腿就跑"那些?
you mean running for cover and that sort of thing?
对      问题是 这是作者的意见
Yes. The problem is, it is the author's opinion.
发表意见不能叫做撒谎
We can't call him a liar for an opinion.
那就说谎言是
Well, say that it's a pack of lies
我在内阁支持核燃料工厂
about my supporting Sellafield in Cabinet
而又公开反对那件事
but speaking against it in public.
好 可问题是 这也不算假      闭嘴 伯纳
Er, yes, but  it is sort of true. shut up, Bernard.
可这怎么能叫谎话连篇呢?
How do we say it's a pack of lies?
首相的回忆和前首相的大相径庭
The PM's recollection is at variance with his predecessor's.
然后说内阁记录支持我的说法
Then say the Cabinet minutes vindicate me completely,
不幸的是 根据30年解密原则 它们25年内不能公开
owing to the 30-year rule, they can't be disclosed for 25 years,
使得他的书不仅不实 更不公平
which makes his book deeply unfair as well as untrue.
抹黑您的部分呢?      抹黑回去
What about the smears against you personally? Smear him.
说他想重写历史 好显得他的治理
Say that he's trying to make his own premiership
不那么惨不忍睹
look a little less disastrous.
暗示他老糊涂了      好
Imply that he's going gaga. Fine.
"岁月流逝加上无据可查 也许模糊了他的记忆"
"Passage of time have perhaps clouded his memory."
好 老糊涂呢?      "对如此高龄的人不必苛责"
What about gaga? "One would expect it from a man of his age."
这就行了?      对 这章本身行了
That do? That's OK for the chapter.
那您想阻止出版的事呢?      说这也是谎话
What about your prevent publication? Say that's lies, too.
"这是对例会发言的断章取义"
"Garbled account of a routine meeting.
"不存在封杀问题"      好
No question of suppression."
您要接受参访吗?      当然不要
Do you want to give interviews? No.
怎么解释呢?      引句原话
Shall I say why? Make it a quote.
"细枝末节 无关国是"
"Insignificant matter of no national importance.
"媒体庸俗化政治的典型体现"
Typical of the media's trivialisation of politics."
这话要归给谁?      亲密内阁同僚
And who shall I attribute that quote to? Close Cabinet colleague.
谢谢 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
简直是灾难啊      当然没那么严重吧
This is a disaster. Oh, surely it's not all that serious.
还不严重? 跟公众说他们的首相不可信?
Telling the public they can't trust their Prime Minister?
他们才不会信呢
They won't believe that.
你觉得不会?      当然不会
Think not? Of course not.
也许会的 不然就是前首相不可信了
They might. Or they couldn't trust their ex-Prime Minister.
对 谢谢 伯纳
Yes, thank you.
他们本来就不该信他
They never could trust him.
谢天谢地 还有我来重建
Thank goodness I've
英国政坛的操守
brought back honesty.
谢天谢地 首相      好 下面把泄漏钉起来
Thank goodness, Prime Minister. Now, about nailing that leak.
请原谅我的咬文嚼字
Sorry to be pedantic,
可如果您钉上漏洞 就又开了个洞
but if you nail a leak, you make another.
我要追查出犯人      是 首相
I want to trace the culprit
还要起诉他      是 首相
and I want a prosecution.
还要给他定罪
Yes, Prime Minister. And I want a conviction.
我们可以尽量追查犯人 也可以起诉
We can try and trace the culprit, we can prosecute,
但在现行政体之下
but under our political system,
政府恐怕很难包办定罪
there are problems about guaranteeing a conviction.
不会吧 跟法官喝点小酒?
Oh, surely. Little drinkie with the judge?
不可思议 绝对不可能对英国法官施压
Unthinkable. There is no way any pressure can be placed on a judge.
那怎么保证定罪?
How does one secure a conviction?
很简单 找个不用施压的法官
Find a judge who won't need any pressure.
问问上院大法官 找个想做高级法官的
Find a judge who's hoping to be made a Lord of Appeal.
然后正义就自有公断了
Then leave justice to take her own impartial and majestic course.
这有用吗?      不一定
That does the trick? Not always.
有时他们太急于罗织罪名 陪审团就是狠心不让
they're so obviously, jury acquits out of bloody-mindedness.
还得找个有常识的法官      那当然
You need a judge with common sense. Oh, yes.
说起来容易找起来难啊
Won't be as easy as you make out.
好吧 你要我怎么跟读者说?
What are you asking me to tell my readers?
我不是要你怎么说
I'm not asking you to tell them anything.
我只是给出我的说法
I'm just putting my side of the story.
不至于吧 何必这么折腾呢
Why the big fuss?
因为我不是双面人 我也没封杀那章
I have not got two faces and suppress that chapter.
能引你这句原话吗?      你不能引我
Can I quote you? You may not quote me
说我不是双面人那句
denying that I have two faces.
值得一试嘛 真不知你急什么 吉姆
It was worth a try. Dunno why you're so upset, Jim.
这章是没说你什么好话
The article doesn't exactly flatter you,
可在政坛上 这种事也是常有的吧
but it's part of the rough and tumble of political life.
我真的觉得 负责任的媒体
A responsible newspaper
不该登这种诽谤 你为什么登?
ought not to print such smears. Why did you?
因为它让我们多卖了10万份
'Cause it sold us over 100,000 extra copies.
你不明白这种指控杀伤力多大吗?
Didn't you realise how damaging that accusation is?
重点就在这 确实杀伤力不小
this is damaging.
而你有权审查 你说你没想封杀它?
you didn't try to stop it?
我当然没有       为什么?
Of course I didn't.
这是个自由国家 言论自由
It's a free country. Freedom of speech.
可它严重伤害你的名誉啊      倒也没那么重
It's damaging to you personally. Not that damaging.
那何必大费周章呢?      我关心的不是我个人的名誉
What's the fuss, then? It's not the damage to me personally I mind.
我是担心国家受的伤      国家?
It's the damage to Britain that I worry about. Britain?
贬损领导层会严重伤害国家威信
Undermining the leadership can damage the nation
国际形象 英镑汇率等等
with foreigners, the pound.
我要你撤销关于封杀的报导
I want you to retract that suppression story. Hm.
这可难了
I don't see how I can.
这有何难 你不是编辑吗?
Of course you can. You're the editor.
对 可编辑不是军队总司令
I'm not a general commanding an army.
我是马戏班班主 只管订演出
I'm the ringmaster of a circus. I book the acts,
管不着杂耍艺人朝哪跳
but I can't tell the acrobats which way to jump!
我建议你 别显得太靠不住
It wouldn't be helpful to make us think we couldn't trust you.
我们当然乐意跟媒体合作
We'd like to cooperate with the press,
但你这是为难我们
but you're making it difficult for us.
首相 我看是你最好别显得
I don't think it'd be helpful if you made it seem as
成心和我们报纸过不去
though you were hostile to our paper.
我们当然乐意和10号合作 可如果要开战...
We like to cooperate with No.10, but if it's war...
不不不 我不是这意思...
No, no, no, no, no, I... No, I wasn't suggesting...
我只是说 我可以让你们
All I meant was that there could be
做独家专访 独家拍照
exclusive interviews, photo opportunities...
如果我撤销报导?      如果你报导真相
If I retract? If you print the truth.
吉姆 我不能改变口径
I have to stick by my story
除非有确凿的反面证据
until I get hard evidence that it's not true.
比如?      比如会议纪要
Such as? The minutes of the meeting.
我看没问题 事关我的清名啊      首相
I don't see why not. My integrity is at stake. Prime Minister...
伯纳 会议纪要和我说的一样 不是吗?
the minutes bear out my version of the meeting
这个 我...
Well, I... er... um...
这个 我...是的
Well, I... er... yes.
好 德雷克 会给你看的
Yes, Derek, you may see them.
我知道事属机密 但这回情况特殊
I know they're usually confidential, but this is a special case.
能刊发吗?      再说吧 我先看一遍
Can I publish them? We'll see. I'll have another look at them.
伯纳 今天下午拿来给我
Bernard, show them to me this afternoon.
请进
Yes?
汉弗莱爵士       你好 伯纳
Sir Humphrey,  Yes, Bernard.
能打扰一下吗?      好的 伯纳
have you got a moment?
我有麻烦了
Er... I've got a problem.
对 伯纳      您知道?
Yes, Bernard. You know?
对 伯纳      您怎么知道
Yes. How?
因为你刚告诉我了 伯纳
Because you've just told me.
您知道我有什么麻烦吗?
Do you know what my problem is?
伯纳 你的麻烦是
Your problem is that
你总说不到重点
you don't ever come to the point.
是是 对不起 首相刚请
Sorry. The PM has just had lunch with
德雷克伯汉吃了午餐 报社主编...
Derek Burnham, the editor...
我知道他是谁 伯纳      好 首相告诉他
I know who he is. The PM told him
内阁会议纪要证实 他没有试图查禁第8章
the minutes confirm that he didn't suppress chapter 8
若有必要 纪要会登报
and that he'd publish them if necessary.
那你有什么麻烦?      纪要还没写呢
So what is your problem? Well, the minutes aren't written yet.
我知道了      那...我该怎么办?
I see. So, er, what should I do?
去写啊 亲爱的伯纳
Write them, dear Bernard.
对 可问题是首相
The problem is the PM
确实试图查禁那章了 不是吗?
did try to suppress the chapter, didn't he?
我不知道 是吗?      您不记得吗?
I don't know. Did he? Don't you remember?
我记得什么不重要 伯纳
What I remember is irrelevant.
如果纪要没说他有 他就没有
If the minutes don't say that he did, then he didn't.
您想要我伪造会议纪要?      我绝对没这种想法
So you want me to falsify the minutes? I want nothing of the sort!
看你了 伯纳 你想要怎样?
What do YOU want, Bernard?
我想有颗清白的良心
I want to have a clear conscience.
清白的良心      对
A clear conscience. Yes.
你几时有了这种奢侈的想法?
When did you acquire this taste for luxuries?
良心是留给政客的 伯纳
Consciences are for politicians, Bernard.
我们是卑微的社会公器
We are humble functionaries
职责不外乎贯彻民意代表的意志
duty is to implement  commands of representatives.
我们怎么可能错 如果我们
How could we be doing anything wrong if
是在执行民意代表的命令?
it has been commanded by those representatives?
这我不能接受 汉弗莱爵士
I can't accept that.
"没有人是孤岛"      正是 伯纳
No man is an island. I agree, Bernard.
"没有人是孤岛 没有人能自全"
"No man is an island, entire of itself;
"因此"
"And therefore
"别再问丧钟为谁而鸣"
"never send to know for whom the bell tolls."
"它正是为你敲响" 伯纳
It tolls for thee, Bernard.
那您看怎么办 汉弗莱爵士?
So what do you suggest, Sir Humphrey?
伯纳 纪要不能面面俱到 对吗?
Minutes do not record everything, do they?
对 当然不能
No, of course not.
会议之中人们就会改变主意 对吗?
People change their minds during a meeting.
对       所以会议是
Yes... So the meeting is
各种变数的集合体 由你选择
a mass of ingredients.
就像烹饪加料      就像...不是像加料 伯纳
Oh, like cooking. Like... No, not like cooking, Bernard.
最好别用这词形容账本或者会议纪要
Better not use that word in connection with books or minutes.
你要从一堆杂乱无章的主张中
You choose from a jumble of ill-digested ideas
筛出一个版本 代表首相的观点
a version which represents the PM's views
也即他期望出现的那一种
as he would, on reflection, have liked them to emerge.
可如果记录不真实...
But if it's not a true record...
纪要的宗旨不在于记录事件本身
The purpose of minutes is not to record events,
而在于保护当事人
it is to protect people.
你不能记录首相言不由衷的话
do not take notes if PM says something he did not mean to
尤其在这些话
particularly if it contradicts
和他公开发言不一致的时候
something he has said publicly.
你要尽量完善他的话 提纲挈领 要讲策略
improve on what has been said, put it in a better order
可这怎么说得通呢?      你是他的仆人
But how do I justify that? You are his servant.
对啊      纪要是为留档做的记录
Oh, yes. A minute is a note for the records
也是共同决议的声明 如果真有决议的话
and a statement of action, if any, that was agreed upon.
会上发生了什么事?      讨论了那本书
What happened at the meeting? Well, the book was discussed.
副检察长提出 查禁它没有法律依据
The SG advised no legal grounds for suppressing
首相是否同意副检察长的话?
And did the PM accept what the Solicitor General had said?
他客观上同意
He accepted the fact there
查禁没有法律依据 可...
were no legal grounds for suppression...
他客观上同意
He accepted the fact
查禁没有法律依据 你看
that there were no legal grounds for suppression. You see?
这是撒谎吗?      不是
Is that a lie? No.
能写成会议纪要吗?      能
Can you write it in the minutes? Yes.
良心感觉如何?      好多了 谢谢您
How's your conscience? Much better, thank you.
伯纳伍列?       什么?
Bernard Woolley?
你的会议纪要今天见报了
Your minutes were published today.
吉姆哈克和副检察长内阁会议的纪要
The minutes of Jim Hacker's meeting.
对 我知道 我赶着上班
I know. I've got to go to work.
就回答几个问题      抱歉 我无可奉告
Answer a few questions. I can't comment.
可你得承认 事情非常可疑      什么?
But it all looks very suspicious. What?
上周四就该发布的
Why did it take so long
怎么拖了这么久?      因为它们没...
to publish them? Because they weren't...
没经过发布审查?
Weren't cleared for publication?
可首相上周四就审查了
But the PM cleared them last Thursday.
对 可我们有
Yes, but there's the Official Secrets Act.
按照 怎么能审查呢?
So how can they be cleared for publication?
首相有权审查一切
The PM can clear anything.
你是说首相不受约束?
Are you saying the PM is not subject to the Official Secrets Act?
这个...不      "不是"还是"确实不受"?
Well... no. No, he is or no, he isn't?
是      你是说规则由哈克说了算
Yes. You're saying that Hacker makes the rules.
不      可你就这么说的
No. That's what you said.
是      就是说在上
Yes. So when it comes to the ACT
首相凌驾于法律之上
the Prime Minister is above the law.
理论上不是      可实践中呢?
Not in theory. But in practice?
无可奉告      真有意思 伯纳
No comment. Very interesting.
听着 我觉得我没有说清楚
Look, I'm not sure I've made myself clear.
你已经说得够清楚了      对了还有
Oh, you've made it very clear.
能不能证实一下
Any truth in the rumour that
你的纪要花了四天才见报
your minutes took four days to appear
是因为哈克先生
because Mr Hacker
只会用两个指头打字?
can only type with two fingers?
抱歉失陪 我真得走了
Excuse me, I must go.
对了 我这些是非官方发言
Oh... er... by the way, I was speaking off the record.
抱歉 伯纳 现在说有点晚了
Sorry, a bit late to say that now.
首相      什么 伯纳?
Prime Minister. Yes, Bernard?
能打扰一下吗?      好的 伯纳
Have you got a moment? Yes, Bernard.
我有个麻烦了
Er... I've got a problem.
说吧 伯纳      呃...是这样
Get on with it, Bernard. Er... yes.
我刚接受了媒体采访
I've just been interviewed by the press.
你? 接受采访?      对 恐怕是的
You? You gave an interview? Er, yes, I'm afraid so.
这事不归你做      我知道
That's not your job. I couldn't help it.
我也没办法啊...就那么发生了
I just... It just happened.
他们包围我 我不得不说      你说了什么?
They trapped me into speaking to them. What did you say?
其实没什么      那你有什么麻烦?
Nothing, really. Well, what's your problem?
他们问我您的事      我的什么事?
They were asking me about you. What about me?
关于您和      还有呢?
About the Official Secrets Act. And?
关于您是否受它约束      我当然受
Whether you were bound by it. Of course I am!
对 您当然受
Of course you are, but it...
可报导...也许不会这么写
it might not come out like that.
你什么意思?
What do you mean?
回想一下我说过的 还有他们说的
Thinking back on what I said and what they said
还有我说您说过的
and what I said you said
还有他们可能会说我说您说过的
and what they may say I said you said
或者他们可能会觉得
or what they may have thought
我说过我觉得的您的观点
I said I thought you thought,
他们也许会说 我说我觉得
they may say I said I thought
您说您觉得...
you said you thought...
说呀 伯纳
Go on, Bernard.
我想我说了 您说您觉得
Well, I think I said you said you thought
您凌驾于法律之上
you were above the law.
你说了那种话?
You said that?!
不是故意的 就那么脱口而出了
Not intentionally. It's just the way it came out.
真对不起 他们拿问题轰炸我
They were asking me all these questions.
伯纳 就算别人提问
What makes you think
谁告诉你非回答不可的?
you have to answer them?
我不知道      我提问你就从来不答啊
I don't know. You've never answered my questions!
我知道...      做了一辈子公务员
I know... After a lifetime in the Civil Service,
整个职业生涯都在回避问题
a career devoted to avoiding questions,
你突然决定今天有问必答 而且是对媒体
you suddenly decide to answer them today and to the press?!
你脑袋进水了吧 伯纳
You must have flipped your lid!
请别冲我吼 首相 我向您保证
Please don't shout at me! I assure you,
我再也不回答任何问题了
I won't answer questions ever again!
叫汉弗莱和比尔过来
Get Humphrey and Bill in here.
去请汉弗莱爵士 还有比尔普雷查德
Send Sir Humphrey in and Bill Pritchard.
如果再碰上这种情况 伯纳
If this question should ever arise again,
你要这样对付提问
this is how you deal with questions.
如果无话可说 就说无可奉告
If you have nothing to say, say nothing.
最好是有话可说
Better still, have something to say
并且说出来 不管他们问什么
and say it, no matter what they ask.
不必在乎问题 只管发表你的意见
Pay no attention to the question. Just make your own statement.
如果他们重提那个问题
If they ask the question again,
就说"问题不在这里"
you say, "That's not the question"
或者"我认为真正问题在于..."
or "I think the real question is..." and then
然后再发表一通你的意见
you make another statement of your own.
泄密调查进展如何?
How's that leak inquiry coming on?
首相 程序马上就开始运转
The wheels will be turning very soon.
马上? 我都交待了一星期了
I asked you a week ago!
你们俩怎么回事?
What's the matter with you two?
真抱歉 首相 我不知道您是认真的
I'm sorry, I had no idea you were serious.
泄密调查一般不会认真追查
Leak inquiries are not usually pursued.
我要这次认真追查 并且立即启动
I want this one pursued rigorously and immediately!
认真追查?      并且立即启动
Rigorously? And immediately.
立即启动?      立即启动
Immediately? Immediately.
您是说您真要查出泄密人?
You mean you REALLY want it pursued?
看我的嘴形 汉弗莱
Watch the lips move, Humphrey.
我要求认真追查 立即启动
I want it pursued. Now.
遵命 首相 如果您是说真的
Very well, Prime Minister, if you're serious.
我会组织真正的调查 如果您真想这么办
I will arrange a genuine inquiry if that's what you really want.
我去找特工处的普劳德探长      谢谢
I'll get Inspector Plod of the Special Branch. Thank you.
我们得想点办法 搞好和媒体的关系
We must do something to improve my relations with the press,
它今天刚严重恶化了
which deteriorated considerably
因为我的私人秘书告诉他们 我自以为
when my private secretary told them I felt
在官方保密问题上凌驾于法律之上
I was above the law when it came to official secrets.
对 你知道低头就好 伯纳
Yes, you may well hang your head.
宪法上怎么排位的 汉弗莱?
What's the constitutional position, Humphrey?
首相 从某种意义上说 伯纳没错
Well, in a sense, Bernard was right.
简而言之 问题在于如何区分
The question, in a nutshell, is what is the difference
违反的行为
between a breach of the Official Secrets Act
和某高级官员做的匿名非正式简报
unattributable, off-the-record briefing by official?
前者 即违反法律 是一项罪名
The former a breach is a criminal offence.
而后者 即简报 却是必要的工作手段
A briefing is essential to keep the wheels turning.
二者之间是有实质区别呢
Is there a difference or is it a matter
还是模棱两可 随心所欲?
of convenience and interpretation?
一次违法行为 可不可能基于
Is it a breach of the act if there is an
一名官员做的匿名非官方简报
unofficial, non-attributable briefing by an official who's been
并且有首相的非官方授权?
unofficially authorised by the Prime Minister?
有首相授权的当然不是      我就是这么说的
Not if it's been authorised by the PM, no. That's what I say.
我当然应该有权决定
I should decide if it's
揭露什么才符合国家利益
in the national interest for something
问题是 官员没这个权力
to be disclosed, not officials.
上周泄密的祸首是一名官员
Last week's leak must've come from an official.
可如果这名官员有官方授权
But what if the official was officially authorised
甚或是非官方授权呢?
or even unofficially authorised?
如果首相发表官方反对
What if the PM officially disapproves of a breach
非官方场合又支持呢?
of the act, but unofficially approves?
那么这就是一次非官方的官方泄密
then it will be unofficially official,
却是官方的非官方泄密
but officially unofficial.
多谢 汉弗莱 你帮了大忙了      多谢 首相
Thank you. You've been a tremendous help. Thank you.
好吧 现在要想法补救
Now, we've got to do something to repair
你们两个本周给我惹的祸
the damage you two have done to me.
我最好再找个主编吃顿饭 找个友好点的
I'd better have lunch with another editor, a friendlier one.
容我打断一下 首相
None of them are
恐怕眼下他们都不大友好
friendly at the moment.
不能给他们个爵位吗?
Couldn't we offer one of them a knighthood?
送人爵位是把双刃剑 对您可好可坏
That can work for or against you.
得看您给了之后 还能否控制他们
Do you have any control over them once you've given it?
哪个编辑都会很高兴吧
Wouldn't they be pleased?
但有了爵位 他们更可能乱说了 百无禁忌了
he may feel free to say what he likes. Nothing to lose.
没错 别指望事后收获感激之情
You don't get gratitude afterwards.
感激不外乎是
Gratitude is merely a lively
对将来好处的热切期盼
expectation of favours to come.
依我看 与其讨好媒体 不如转移他们注意力?
May I suggest that we distract the press?
我们给他们个故事      比如说?
Let's give them a story. Such as?
发动个战争之类的
Start a war, that sort of thing.
发动战争?      小战争就行
Start a war?! Only a small war.
容我打断一下
Um... if I might intervene.
就算小战争可能也过火了
Even a small war would be overkill.
您何不驱逐76名苏联外交官员呢?
Why don't you expel 76 Soviet diplomats?
这是惯例 每次我们
That's always been our practice when we wish
想转移媒体注意力都这么办
to ensure the press lose interest in something.
我不能这样      您会上头条
I can't do that. Great headline.
"政府大破赤色间谍网" 多爱国
"Government cracks down on red spy ring." Very patriotic.
一定得是没人能否认的消息
It must be a story that nobody can disprove.
就算被否认人们也相信
And which will be believed even if it's denied.
"苏联大使司机乃是克格勃中将"
"Soviet ambassador's chauffeur is Lieutenant General in KGB."
我不能这样 我花了几周辛辛苦苦缓和局势
I can't do that. I've been working at this detente for weeks.
这是眼下唯一有进展的工作
It's the only thing that IS working at the moment.
你说呢 伯纳? 你不是爆料专家吗
What do you think? You're good at getting in the papers.
皇家事件如何?      比如呢?
What about a royal event? Such as?
订婚 离婚 或者怀孕
An engagement, a divorce, a pregnancy.
你能安排吗?
You can arrange that?
他读泄密调查报告了吗?
Has he read the leak inquiry report?
他正在读 我们怎么办?
Yes. How do we handle it?
很难办 泄密调查查出责任人
Very difficult. There is almost no precedent for
几乎没有先例可循
handling a leak inquiry which finds the culprit.
更别说责任人还是高级公务员
Especially when it's a senior civil servant.
不过我看我们能救他
I think we can save him.
怎么救? 他出席会议了 他招认了
How? He was at the meeting. He's owned up.
就是他干的 毫无疑问 对吗?      会有疑问的
There can't be any doubt. There's going to be.
汉弗莱 看到了吗? 被我猜中了
There, Humphrey, you see? Just as I suspected.
我要起诉那个能源部新闻秘书
I want that press officer at the Department of Energy prosecuted.
根据官方保密法...
The official secret act...
恕我反对 首相      你反对是吗 汉弗莱?
I think not... You think not?
就因为他是公务员?
Because he's a civil servant?
当然不是 首相
No, PRIME MINISTER
是因为这违反您的利益
because it is not in your interests.
违反我的利益? 惩办一个
That somebody should be punished for
把政府贬得一钱不值的人?
undermining government?
首相 副检察长
The Attorney General
说不可能成功起诉
says that a prosecution would not succeed
因为不涉及安全问题
because there are no security implications.
我不管 就当杀鸡儆猴吧
At least it'd make an example of him.
他还建议 如果我们起诉
He advises that if we prosecute, we must
我们必须也请特工处调查
undertake a similar Special Branch inquiry
早先第5章的泄露
into the earlier leak of chapter 5
您知道 您在库朗的成就
your success in Kumran.
这个...完全是两码事
Ah... well... that was completely different.
何以见得?      那个完全无害嘛
May one ask why? Well, it was harmless.
副检察长说要么两次都无害 要么都有害
AG says that either both are harmless or neither.
要我去通知特工处 调查第5章的泄露吗?
Shall I ask Special Branch to work on the chapter 5 leak?
好吧 不起诉了 炒掉那新闻秘书
Drop the prosecution, but sack the press officer.
这也很难 有证据显示
That could be difficult. There is evidence
他不是自作主张
he was not acting on his own initiative.
怎么讲?      是他上司国务大臣的授意
Meaning? They were his Secretary of State's wishes.
什么?      对 显然
What?! Yes
国务大臣很乐意
The Secretary was not displeased
被写成内阁最能干的大臣 他吩咐新闻秘书
at being described as the ablest minister
他不仅不想封杀这一章 还希望它马上见报
he wouldn't mind seeing it in the press at once.
并且提到 它只能如此面世
With reference to the fact that it might not otherwise be read
因为10号施压要查禁它      你肯定吗?
because of an attempt by No.10 to censor it. You sure of this?
我肯定那位新闻秘书会这么解释
I am sure that's what the press officer's explanation will be
当他以非法解雇为名
when his case for wrongful dismissal
起诉到劳工法庭的时候
comes up before the industrial tribunal.
非法解雇?      他会辩解说
Wrongful dismissal? He'll argue
他是执行暗示的命令
he was following an implied order.
实行他的国务大臣的授意
Carrying out his Secretary of State's wishes.
所以我也不能炒他      不能
So I can't sack him.
那我能炒谁?      首相 如果您非要炒掉谁
Well, who can I sack? Well, if you must sack somebody,
唯一人选是能源大臣
the only candidate is the Energy Secretary
他要为他的部负责
who is responsible for his department.
这怎么行 我上周刚失去一名大臣
I can't do that. I lost one minister last week.
不能这周又炒一个吧
I can't sack another this week.
正是 首相 失去一名内阁大臣
Quite, Prime Minister. To lose one Cabinet minister
可以看作不幸
may be regarded as a misfortune.
失去两个就像是识人不明了
To lose both looks like carelessness.
谢谢 伯纳 还有 首相
Thank you, Bernard. Furthermore, Prime Minister,
能源大臣没有泄密 也没授意泄密
as the Energy Secretary did not do the leaking,
他也可以告我们非法解雇
he might sue for wrongful dismissal as well.
那我怎么办? 媒体都吵着要调查结果
The press is clamouring for the result of this inquiry.
新闻办...起草了这份声明
Well, the press office... has drafted this statement.
"通讯故障...误解..."
"Communications breakdown... misunderstanding...
"...动机是好的...将以内部规章处理"
"will be dealt with by internal procedures."
这是漂白      不不 不完全是
This is a whitewash. Not really.
它把责任平摊了
It shares out the blame equally.
可以称之为漂灰
More of a grey wash.
看着还是像我要查禁它
Still looks like I tried to suppress that chapter.
我该怎么办 汉弗莱?
What am I to do?
也许我们应该把消息公开
Perhaps we should send the story out,
然后扼杀它
but smother it.
扼杀它? 你是说...
Smother it? You mean...
首相 我正打算告诉您
Oh, Prime Minister, I've been meaning to tell you.
外交部文件里有些消息很让人担心
There's some very worrying information on the Foreign Office files
是关于苏联使馆
about espionage in the Soviet embassy
和贸易代表团的间谍活动
and trade delegation.
不会吧      有不利证据指向许多外交官员
No? Evidence against a lot of diplomats.
多少?
How many?
76位
汉弗莱 我看是该铁腕一下了
You know, I think the time has come to be firm.
毫无疑问      这关系到领土主权问题
Absolutely. The defence of the realm is at stake.
千真万确      驱逐他们
Precisely. Expel them.
我要媒体今天就得到消息
And I want the press told today.
同时进行
At the same time...
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组
-==www.RagBear.com==-
欢迎加入